# **MENG WANG**

mengwang@ece.ubc.ca 4025 Fred Kaiser Building, 2332 Main Mall Vancouver, BC, Canada V6T 1Z4

## **SUMMARY**

I am currently a 4th-year Ph.D. candidate in Computer Engineering at the University of British Columbia, where my research focuses on practical quantum computing for the NISQ era and beyond. My academic journey has involved building advanced quantum circuit simulators and optimizing the execution efficiency of variational quantum algorithms. During my previous internship at Pacific Northwest National Laboratory, I gained valuable experience in high-performance computing for quantum simulations and also engaged in interdisciplinary collaboration with experts in Chemistry and Physics.

## **EDUCATION**

Ph.D in Electrical and Computer Engineering The University of British Columbia Advisor: Dr.Prashant Nair	September 2020 - Present Vancouver, BC, Canada	
BASc in Computer Engineering The University of British Columbia Graduated with Distinction	September 2017 - June 2020 Vancouver, BC, Canada	
Associate of Science Langara College	Nance  September 2015 - July 2017  Vancouver, BC, Canada	
AWARDS		
Faculty of Applied Science Graduate Award  The annual award, subject to annual review and criteria fulfillment.	2021, 2022, 2023, UBC	
APSC Capstone Faculty Award	May 2020, UBC	
Dean's Honour List	Jun~2019,~UBC	
Special Progressing Award	Feb 2016, Langara College	
Entrance Scholarship	Jul 2015, Langara College	

## CONFERENCE PUBLICATIONS

1.	ASPLOS'24	Meng Wang, Bo Fang, Ang Li, and Prashant Nair Red-QAOA: Efficient Variational Optimization through Circuit Reduction International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems, 2024
2.	MICRO-57 In Review	Meng Wang, Bo Fang, Ang Li, and Prashant Nair INFORMR: Leveraging Informed Restarts for Efficient and Scalable QAOA Execution
3.	MICRO-57 In Review	Meng Wang, Poulami Das, and Prashant Nair Qoncord: A Multi-Device Job Scheduling Framework for Variational Quantum Algorithms

4. MICRO-57 Avinash Kumar, Meng Wang, Chenxu Liu, Ang Li, Prashant Nair, and Poulami Das
In Review QONTEXTS: Quantum Context Switching To Mitigate Attacks In Multi-programmed Sys-

tems

5. SC'24 Meng Wang, Swamit Tannu, and Prashant Nair

In Review TQSim: A Case for Reuse-Focused Tree-Based Quantum Circuit Simulation

6. Fei Hua, Chenxu Liu, **Meng Wang**, Yuwei Jin, Muqing Zheng, Minghao Guo, Gushu Li,

Draft in Progress Bo Peng, Samuel Stein, Yufei Ding, Travis Humble, Eddy Z. Zhang, and Ang Li

QASMTrans: A QASM Quantum Transpiler Framework for NISQ Devices

7. Fei Hua, Yuwei Jin, Ang Li, Yanhao Chen, Ari Hayes, Chi Zhang, Meng Wang, Chenxu

Draft in Progress Liu, Yipeng Huang, Samuel Stein, Eddy.Z Zhang

A Software Approach for Mitigating Crosstalk of Two-qubit Gates in Quantum Hardware

#### JOURNAL PUBLICATIONS

1. Quantum Chenxu Liu, Meng Wang, Samuel Stein, Yufei Ding, and Ang Li
In Review Quantum Memory: A Missing Piece in Quantum Computing Units

#### WORKSHOP PUBLICATIONS

1. QCS'23 Meng Wang, Fei Hua, Chenxu Liu, Nicholas Bauman, Karol Kowalski, Daniel Claudino,

Travis Humble, Prashant Nair, Ang Li

Enabling Scalable VQE Simulation on Leading HPC Systems

The International Conference for High Performance Computing, Networking, Storage, and

Analysis Workshop: Quantum Computing Softwares, 2023.

2. QCCC'23 Meng Wang, Bo Fang, Ang Li, and Prashant Nair

Efficient QAOA Optimization using Directed Restarts and Graph Lookup

The Second International Workshop on Quantum Classical Cooperative Computing.

#### WORK EXPERIENCE

#### Pacific Northwest National Laboratory

Ph.D. Research Intern. Mentor: Ang Li, Bo Fang

October 2022 - August 2023 Richland, WA, USA

- Participated in developing simulation frameworks leveraging leading HPC systems including Frontier, Summit, and Perlmutter to simulate large-scale quantum circuits on GPU clusters. The simulation framework is open-sourced at https://github.com/pnnl/NWQ-Sim.
- Led research improving the efficiency of classical optimization in Quantum Approximated Optimization Algorithm (QAOA), yielding two publications: Red-QAOA (accepted at **ASPLOS'24**) proposing a circuit reduction technique, and INFORMR (in progress for **ISCA'24**) introducing an informed restart approach.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

#### Teaching Assistant at UBC

CPEN 312 - Digital Systems and Microcomputers

CPSC 322 - Introduction to Artificial Intelligence

APSC 160 - Introduction to Computation in Engineering Design

CPEN 411 - Computer Architecture

CPSC 340 - Machine Learning and Data Mining

Vancouver, BC, Canada

January 2024 - April 2024

July 2022 - August 2022

January 2022 - April 2022

September 2021 - December 2021

January 2021 - April 2021

## **SKILLS**

# Programming skills:

Verilog, C, C++, CUDA, HIP, MPI, Java, Python, ARMv7 Assembly, Racket.

# Software Packages:

Qiskit, Qulacs.

# Hardware:

System-on-Chip (SoC) FPGA, Raspberry Pi, Arduino.